"How to Boost Collagen Synthesis with Diet"
As we age, the synthesis
of collagen decreases
by about 1 percent a year,
which may contribute
to the development of wrinkles.
Though we don't have evidence
that collagen is superior to any
other proteins for aging skin,
those who do want to try it
are advised to contact
the manufacturers
to clarify its source.
Most collagen supplements don't
disclose this information
and for good reason.
Terrestrial sources
can include a witch's brew
of kangaroo and rat tails,
duck feet, horse tendons,
alligator bones,
and frog skin.
Aquatic sources are mainly
from fish skins, bones, heads,
scales, fins, and entrails.
Recommended questions
for manufacturers include
"What measures were used
to protect against
contamination or adulteration?
If sourced from fish,
were low-mercury fish used?
If sourced from cows,
what steps were taken
to ensure that
no brain or nervous system
matter was included,
in order to prevent
prion disease?"
In the United States,
collagen is exempt
from FDA prohibitions
against using risky tissues
like brains--
prohibitions in place
to protect consumers
against bovine spongiform
encephalopathy,
also known as mad cow disease.
So, for food safety,
religious, ethical,
or allergy-related reasons,
there have been calls
for non-animal alternatives.
For example, 2 to 4 percent
of the population
is allergic to bovine collagen.
To solve the mad cow conundrum,
there have been calls
to genetically engineer
cattle without prions
to "offer a safe source
of collagen-based materials."
But why not just get
plants to make it?
A technique has been perfected
to produce collagen from plants,
but it has not yet reached
commercial viability.
It's hard to beat
the cost of feet.
But what about all of the vegan
collagen products on the market?
If you look closely,
you'll see the small print:
vegan collagen builder
or vegan collagen booster.
It's not actually collagen,
since collagen
is made by animals,
but you're an animal,
you make collagen.
So they're suggesting
their supplements
can boost production,
but since it appears
none of them have actually
been put to the test,
I assume it's all
a load of bunk.
But there are some
foods and nutrients
that have been investigated.
Researchers burned the butts
of 20 women with a UV lamp
before and after half of them
ate three tablespoons
of tomato paste each day
for three months.
And there was a significant
reduction in MMP-1 levels
in the derrieres of those
who had been randomized
to the tomatoes.
(That's a major
collagen-eating enzyme
that plays a role in skin aging
caused by the sun.)
Butt biopsies also show
that the amount of beta-carotene
found in about
one and a third cup
of sweet potato
can boost collagen production
as much as four-fold
within three months.
To test the effects of greens,
Korean researchers
randomized older women
to the amount of chlorophyll
found in a few tablespoons
of cooked spinach a day.
After three months,
skin biopsies showed
a significant increase
in collagen production,
accompanied by an increase
in skin elasticity
and a decrease
in facial wrinkles.
Unfortunately, this was just
a before-and-after comparison
to baseline study
with no control group,
but there have been
placebo-controlled
randomized trials,
and of kale no less!
Compared to placebo, there was
a significant improvement
in a noninvasive measure
of skin collagen status
after 10 months
of being randomized
to an extract of curly kale.
The researchers concluded
that "a healthy lifestyle
including a diet
rich in carotenoids
is the best prevention strategy
against premature skin aging."
That led to dermatology
journal commentaries
with titles like "Eat plenty
of green leafy vegetables
for protection from
the pro-aging rays of the sun,"
but might it actually be
more than that?
Sulforaphane, the cruciferous
compound in kale and broccoli,
may be able to mobilize
cellular defenses
that protect skin
against damage by UV radiation,
as well as mitigate
the premature skin aging
induced by air pollution
particulate matter,
though this was on skin cells
in a Petri dish.
Soybean compounds can increase
collagen deposition
and prevent wrinkles in mice,
but what about in people?
Given improvements
of skin aging
seen with menopausal
hormone therapy
but concerned
about the side effects,
researchers in Brazil
tried giving phytohormones,
plant hormones in the form
of soy phytoestrogens.
Twenty-nine
postmenopausal women
were given the amount
in four servings a day
of soy foods for six months.
Unfortunately,
there was no control group,
but they did take skin biopsies
before and after
and found a significant
improvement in skin thickness,
along with increased
collagen content
and elastic fibers.
The biopsies
of 25 out of 29 women
showed an increase in collagen.
You could also throw in
some vitamin C-rich foods,
as vitamin C appears
to stimulate collagen production
from human skin cells.
Defective wound healing
has long been known
as a major manifestation
of scurvy,
the vitamin C-deficiency
disease.
In fact, a remarkable series
of grisly experiments
performed on British
conscientious objectors
during World War II
involved being subjected
to cuts and stab wounds
after being randomized
to different levels
of vitamin C.
The researchers found
that the average
daily vitamin C intake
to prevent weak scar formation
was about 95 milligrams,
which is actually higher than
the current recommendations
but nothing you can't get
from half a bell pepper.
Vitamin B12 also appears
to be necessary
for maximum collagen synthesis,
which may explain why
collagen synthesis rates
appear to be about 10 percent
lower in vegetarians,
because the prevalence
of B12 deficiency
among those eating
plant-based diets is so high.
That's one of many reasons
why it's critically important
that everyone consuming
a plant-based diet
ensures a regular, reliable
source of vitamin B12.